[Cheers and applause]
(Mouthing): Thank you!
Chief Justice Roberts, President Carter,
President Clinton, President Bush,
President Obama, fellow Americans,
and people of the world, thank you.
[Cheers and applause]
We, the citizens of America, are
now joined in a great national effort
to rebuild our country and restore
its promise for all of our people.
Together we will determine the
course of America, and the world,
for many, many years to come.
We will face challenges,
we will confront hardships,
but we will get the job done.
Every four years, we
gather on these steps
to carry out the orderly and
peaceful transfer of power –
and we are grateful to President Obama,
and first lady Michelle Obama,
for their gracious aid
throughout this transition.
They have been magnificent.
Thank you.
[Cheers and applause]
Today's ceremony, however,
has very special meaning –
because today, we are not
merely transferring power
from one administration to another,
or from one party to another –
but we are transferring power
from Washington DC,
and giving it back to you, the people.
[Cheers and applause]
For too long, a small group
in our nation's capital
has reaped the rewards of government,
while the people have borne the cost.
Washington flourished, but the
people did not share in its wealth.
Politicians prospered, but the
jobs left, and the factories closed.
The establishment protected itself,
but not the citizens of our country.
Their victories have
not been your victories;
their triumphs have not
been your triumphs;
and while they celebrated
in our nation's capital,
there was little to celebrate for
struggling families all across our land.
[Cheers and applause]
That all changes, starting
right here and right now,
because this moment is your
moment: it belongs to you.
[Cheers and applause]
It belongs to everyone
gathered here today,
and everyone watching
all across America;
this is your day, this
is your celebration,
and this, the United States
of America, is your country.
[Cheers and applause]
What truly matters is not which
party controls our government,
but whether our government
is controlled by the people.
[Distant cheers and applause]
January 20th, 2017, will
be remembered as the day
the people became the
rulers of this nation again.
[Cheers and applause]
The forgotten men and women of our
country will be forgotten no longer.
[Cheers and applause]
Everyone is listening to you now.
You came by the tens of millions
to become part of a historic movement,
the likes of which the world
has never seen before.
[Distant cheers and applause]
At the centre of this movement
is a crucial conviction that a
nation exists to serve its citizens.
Americans want great
schools for their children,
safe neighbourhoods for their families,
and good jobs for themselves.
These are just and reasonable demands
of righteous people and a righteous public.
But for too many of our citizens,
a different reality exists:
mothers and children trapped
in poverty in our inner cities;
rusted out factories scattered like tombstones
across the landscape of our nation;
an education system flushed with cash,
but which leaves our young and beautiful
students deprived of all knowledge;
and the crime, and the gangs, and the
drugs that have stolen too many lives
and robbed our country of
so much unrealised potential.
This American carnage stops
right here and stops right now.
[Cheers and applause]
We are one nation, and
their pain is our pain,
their dreams are our dreams, and
their success will be our success.
We share one heart, one home,
and one glorious destiny.
The oath of office I take today is an
oath of allegiance to all Americans.
[Distant cheers and applause]
For many decades, we've
enriched foreign industry
at the expense of American industry;
subsidised the armies of other countries,
while allowing for the very
sad depletion of our military;
we've defended other nations' borders,
while refusing to defend our own;
[Cheers and applause]
and spent trillions and
trillions of dollars overseas,
while America's infrastructure has
fallen into disrepair and decay.
We've made other countries rich,
while the wealth, strength,
and confidence of our country
has dissipated over the horizon.
One by one, the factories
shuttered and left our shores,
with not even a thought
about the millions and
millions of American workers
that were left behind.
The wealth of our middle class
has been ripped from their homes,
and then redistributed
all across the world.
But that is the past – and now,
we are looking only to the future.
[Cheers and applause]
We assembled here today
are issuing a new decree
to be heard in every city, in every foreign
capital, and in every hall of power;
from this day forward, a new
vision will govern our land –
from this day forward, it's going to
be only 'America first,' 'America first.'
[Cheers and applause]
Every decision on trade, on taxes,
on immigration, on foreign affairs,
will be made to benefit American
workers and American families.
We must protect our borders from
the ravagers of other countries,
making our products, stealing our
companies, and destroying our jobs.
[Cheers and applause]
Protection will lead to great
prosperity and strength.
I will fight for you with
every breath in my body,
and I will never ever let you down.
[Resonant cheers and applause]
America will start winning again,
winning like never before.
[Cheers and applause]
We will bring back our jobs,
we will bring back our borders,
we will bring back our wealth,
and we will bring back our dreams.
[Cheers and applause]
We will build new roads, and
highways, and bridges, and airports,
and tunnels, and railways,
all across our wonderful nation.
We will get our people off
of welfare, and back to work,
rebuilding our country with
American hands and American labour.
[Cheers and applause]
We will follow two simple rules:
'Buy American' and 'Hire American.'
[Cheers and applause]
We will seek friendship and goodwill
with the nations of the world,
but we do so with the understanding
that it is the right of all nations
to put their own interests first.
We do not seek to impose
our way of life on anyone –
but rather, to let it
shine as an example;
we will shine for
everyone to follow.
[Cheers and applause]
We will reinforce old alliances
and form new ones,
and unite the civilised world
against radical Islamic terrorism,
which we will eradicate completely
from the face of the earth!
[Cheers and applause]
At the bedrock of our politics
will be a total allegiance to
the United States of America,
and through our loyalty
to our country,
we will rediscover our
loyalty to each other.
When you open your
heart to patriotism,
there is no room for prejudice.
[Cheers and applause]
The Bible tells us how
good and pleasant it is
when God's people live
together in unity.
We must speak our minds openly,
debate our disagreements honestly,
but always pursue solidarity.
When America is united,
America is totally unstoppable.
[Cheers and applause]
There should be no fear –
we are protected, and we
will always be protected;
we will be protected by the
great men and women
of our military and
law enforcement,
and most importantly,
[Cheers and applause]
we will be protected by God.
Finally, we must think big,
and dream even bigger.
In America, we understand
that a nation is only living
as long as it is striving.
We will no longer accept politicians
who are all talk and no action –
constantly complaining, but
never doing anything about it.
[Cheers and applause]
The time for empty talk is over.
Now arrives the hour of action.
[Distant cheers and applause]
Do not allow anyone to tell
you that it can not be done.
No challenge can match the heart,
and fight, and spirit of America.
We will not fail; our country
will thrive and prosper again.
We stand at the birth
of a new millennium –
ready to unlock the
mysteries of space,
to free the Earth from
the miseries of disease,
and to harness the energies, industries,
and technologies of tomorrow.
A new national pride will stir our souls,
lift our sights, and heal our divisions.
It's time to remember that old wisdom
our soldiers will never forget:
that whether we are black,
or brown, or white,
we all bleed the same
red blood of patriots.
[Cheers and applause]
We all enjoy the same
glorious freedoms,
and we all salute the
same great American flag.
[Cheers and applause]
And whether a child is born
in the urban sprawl of Detroit,
or the windswept plains of Nebraska,
they look up at the same night sky,
they fill their heart with the same dreams,
and they are infused with the breath
of life by the same almighty creator.
[Cheers and applause]
So to all Americans, in every city
near and far, small and large –
from mountain to mountain, from
ocean to ocean, hear these words:
you will never be ignored again.
[Cheers and applause]
Your voice, your hopes, and your
dreams will define our American destiny.
And your courage and goodness and
love will forever guide us along the way.
Together, we will make America strong
again, we will make America wealthy again,
we will make America proud again,
we will make America safe again,
and yes – together, we will
make America great again.
Thank you, God bless you,
and God bless America.
Thank you. God bless America.